<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon lately preached at court, before His Majesty, in ordinary attendance: by VVilliam Peterson, D.D. and Deane of Exeter. Chaplaine to His Majesty.</title>
            <author>Peterson, William, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E151_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E151[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon lately preached at court, before His Majesty, in ordinary attendance: by VVilliam Peterson, D.D. and Deane of Exeter. Chaplaine to His Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Peterson, William, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath: Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James V, 13 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156762:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Lately Preached AT COVRT, Before His <hi>MAJESTY, In Ordinary Attendance:</hi> BY VVILLIAM PETERSON, <hi>D. D.</hi> And DEANE of EXETER. Chaplaine to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath: Butter.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:156762:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156762:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before <hi>His MAJESTIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JAMES Chap. 5. ver. 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Is any amongst you afflicted? let him pray: Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalmes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere have we a double Queſtion propounded, with a double Anſwer; a Direction both for proſperity and adverſity; for the mourning weede, and the wedding Garment; <hi>Pray</hi> and <hi>Sing.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Is any one afflicted? let him pray;</hi> here is a reſtorative againſt ſadneſſe. Secondly, <hi>Is any merry,</hi> becauſe of Peace within his walls, or plenteouſneſſe within his Palaces, or becauſe his corne and his oyle is increaſed? <hi>let him ſing;</hi> here is a preſervative to continue theſe Bleſſings.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156762:3"/>
            <p>The firſt Propoſition it is of affliction, a theame moſt ſuitable with theſe ſad and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented times, and therefore I meane to make it the onely ſubject of my enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>We finde the Propoſition to be indefinite, no perſon appointed, no time defined, no place en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, but it concernes all men, at all times, and in all places, whoſoever, howſoever, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and whereſoever afflicted he muſt pray.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whoſoever, the poore as well as the rich, and the rich as well as the poore, for whilſt we are in this world, we are all ſubject to ſundrie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, griefes of body, defects of minde, our bodies being the Anvils of paine and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and our mindes the hives of unnumbred cares; yea, what dangers at any time are immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and what evils at this preſent hang over our heads, God himſelfe doth know and not we. We ſee by daily experience, that thoſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be neereſt at hand, readieſt to breake in ſuddainly upon us, which we in regard of time and circumſtance may imagine to be fartheſt off, for our whole life it is nothing elſe but a mixture of good and evill; and joy and ſorrow in this life are ſo woven one within the other, that (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) to looke for one without the other, were to aime at things impoſſible; for as impoſſible is it in this life to have an eſtate without all trouble, as to have a faire day without ſome clouds: So that this preſent life of ours, it is nothing elſe, but the beginning and end of a Tragedie, a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of many miſeries, inchained one within an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156762:3"/>One cries out <hi>My belly my belly,</hi> with the Prophet; another <hi>My ſonne my ſonne,</hi> with <hi>David;</hi> another <hi>My father my father,</hi> with <hi>Eliſha;</hi> Every childe of God hath ſome complaint or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make his cheekes wet, and his heart heavie. <hi>Eſay</hi> had <hi>ſerram,</hi> Chriſt himſelfe had <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, John</hi> Baptiſt <hi>ſecurim,</hi> and <hi>Stephen lapidem; haec eſt conditio veritatis.</hi> The Sodomites make <hi>Lot</hi> their Tabret, and the wicked make ſongs on <hi>David;</hi> Chriſt he doth not broach his beſt wine firſt for his Diſciples, but tells them plainly, that they muſt firſt drinke of thoſe bitter waters of Marah, before they can drinke of that ever-living well, of which whoſoever drinkes ſhall never thirſt more. For as gold (that moſt valued and reſtorative metall) paſſeth ſeven times the flame, before his purification be accompliſhed; ſo it is the will of that unconfined Spirit, that all thoſe that he highly prizeth, ſhould ſeventy ſeven times enter the hot furnace of affliction, that ſo they may be purified and made cleane from the filth of ſinne: And thus we ſee how our pilgrimage here on earth, is like Iſraels journey through the wilderneſſe, ſometimes fiery ſerpents, ſometimes want of water, ſometime enemies doe oppreſſe us. It is like the paſſage through the red Sea, we have the waters on the right hand, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on the left hand, and therefore we had neede to ſtand upon our guard to <hi>watch and pray leſt we fall into temptation.</hi> Let us not then neglect this happie means of our deliverance, both from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and approaching evills, but let us with all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156762:4"/>fervencie and humility, poure out our Prayers and Supplications unto God, to deſire him to divert thoſe heavie judgements, which at this preſent ſeeme to threaten our danger in great proportion, and that he would be pleaſed to put a period to all thoſe untimely differences and diſcordances now amongſt us, that ſo this little Iſland of ours which ſtands divided from all the world, may by this happie conjunction, live in peace and unity within it ſelfe. And thus for the generality of the perſon, All of us are ſubject to divers incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, and therefore all muſt pray.</p>
            <p>Now follows the ſecond circumſtance, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever afflicted we muſt pray: howſoever, either for manner or for meaſure. Firſt, for manner, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever afflicted, either in ſoule or body, either with ſickneſſe or poverty, either for want of any good thing, or the repulſe of any bad thing, here is thy remedy, <hi>pray,</hi> either for affliction happened, or that will happen: Is there any good that thou deſireſt? Call to God: Is there any evill thou deteſteſt? Pray againſt it; whether it be <hi>malum poenae,</hi> or <hi>malum culpae:</hi> Doth any evill of ſinne trouble thee? Call to God: Doth any evill of puniſhment vexe thee; either corporall or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? He can helpe thee, either in turning it away before it come, or removing it already come, or elſe in leſſening or extenuating it. <hi>Cum duplican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur lateres, tum venit Moſes,</hi> when the Iſraelites burdens were greateſt, then came Moſes to help them; and when the righteous mans caſe is moſt dangerous, then ſtands God moſt readie to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156762:4"/>him. And thus for the manner of our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Howſoever afflicted we muſt pray.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the meaſure of our affliction; Howſoever likewiſe afflicted we muſt pray. We muſt not complaine that our affliction is greater then wee can ſuſtaine, for every one ſhall have a burden according as he can beare, <hi>Veniſon for ſick Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 27. <hi>Milke for young babes,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Herbs for the weake, Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>And ſtrong meate for men of age; the bruiſed reede God will not breake, and the ſmoaking flax he will not quench.</hi> The righteous muſt expect a greater tryall then another, becauſe God hath given him a greater meaſure of faith then other. For as a workeman when he eſpies a ſtrong piece of timber, he makes uſe of it, and puts it to be the underpropper of the houſe or palace he hath to build; but as for other pieces that are crackt, and able to ſupport no weight, he paints them over, and placeth them onely for ornament and ſhew: So the Founder of this faire fabrique, when he findes a ſoule able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe and undertake things of weight, he layes as heavie a burden upon it, as it is able to ſtand under, but as for ſofter ſpirits, he lets them lye idle, as not being able to ſupport any thing for him, nor yet of ſtrength ſufficient to doe him any acceptable ſervice. Admit I could ſay, that I knew nothing at all in my conſcience whereby I ſhould deſerve any affliction, calumnie, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to fall upon me, ſhall I therefore preſently murmur and repine, and call Gods Juſtice into queſtion? ſurely no, I will rather lay my hand
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156762:5"/>upon my mouth, and attend with patience the farther manifeſtation of his good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. It may be theſe troubles that are falne upon us are ſent of God, for the exerciſe of our humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: This I am ſure, that <hi>all things worke together for the beſt to them that feare God:</hi> For as it is in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if you examine them part by part, you may perhaps not finde one good face amongſt them all, but exceptions may be taken either at the breadth, or narrowneſſe of the forehead, or elſe at the colour, or dimneſſe of the eye, or elſe at the ſharpneſſe of the chin, or the length of the noſe, or thinneſſe of the lip; But take all theſe parts together, and they may doe very well, and helpe to make up a ſeemely and well-compoſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: ſo in thoſe things which are ſent unto us of God, if we examine them ſeverally, part by part, we may perhaps finde juſt matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and thinke that there may be diſorder and injuſtice in the things of God; but if we take them all together, we ſhal find the compoſition admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and of excellent uſe and benefit unto us, and we ſhall ſee, that God neither effectually worketh nor permiſſively ſuffereth any thing to be done unto the righteous, but onely for their good, and their amendment, and therefore to murmure or repine againſt God, or to expoſtulate and aske the queſtion, why God doth afflict one man more ſeverely then another; thou maiſt with as much reaſon move the queſtion, why God loves one man better then another: Tell me why the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian preſcribes thee a greater proportion of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156762:5"/>Rubarbe then another, becauſe he doth experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally finde that ſuch a one will be moved more with one dram, then thou canſt be with three. Some man is ſooner moved of God by the loſſe of his crop of corne, then another by the burning of his houſe, by the loſſe of his wife and children. For though the conſciences of ſome be ſuch, as oile and butter may ſupple them, yet the moſt part are ſo over-grown with hardneſſe, as they require ſtrong and potent corraſives to make an entrance into them. And thus for the manner and meaſure of our afflictions, howſoever afflicted we muſt pray.</p>
            <p>Now follows the third circumſtance, When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever afflicted we muſt pray: whenſoever, that is, ſo oft as we are afflicted, ſo ſoone as wee are afflicted, and ſo long as we are afflicted.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſo oft as we are afflicted, for <hi>Gods wayes are not like wans wayes:</hi> If a beggar come once or twice to our doores, we may perhaps be ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, as to relieve him and give him almes; but if he hant our houſe, we withdraw our bounty, and give no longer: But God is alwayes ready to beſtow his bleſſings, (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) but that the perverſeneſſe of man doth hinder. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem,</hi> doe thou beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>how often would Chriſt have gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy children, as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, but thou wouldeſt not? For as a father pitties his onely ſonne</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>ſo God ſhews compaſsion on thoſe that love and call upon him.</hi> Yea, Gods love is ſo great, that nothing can be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156762:6"/>compared with it; for what love ſhall I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare unto his love? the love of a woman? It is great indeed, but yet the love of <hi>Jonathan</hi> to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is greater then it: To the love of a mother? Here is a greater degree then the former; but yet this is not ſo certaine and infallible as Gods love. <hi>Can a mother forget her childe, and not have compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the ſonne of her wombe?</hi> as ſome may be, yea ſome we know have beene ſo unnaturall, <hi>yet will not I forget thee,</hi> ſaith God to his diſconſolate and afflicted Sion. And therefore untill you finde whom ye may compare with God, you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finde any love to be compared with his love; for as it is in it ſelfe without beginning, ſo it is towards all others without ending; and though <hi>his mercie be above all his workes,</hi> yet it doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it ſelfe to the leaſt of his workes: yea, ſo great is the love of God to mankinde, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſome of the Schoolemen make it one of their curious queſtions, Whether the love of God to the world, or his love to his onely Son bee greateſt. I finde him in holy Scriptures ſometimes compared to a Father, ſometimes to a Mother, ſometimes to a friend, ſometimes to a husband, that ſo by theſe familiar ſpeeches, we might aſpire unto ſome ſenſe and knowledge of his indulgent and compaſſionate nature. He is <hi>Pater amoris,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Jerome</hi>) and will helpe; and he is <hi>Pater poteſtatis,</hi> and can helpe us. Faint not then under any temptation or trouble, but howſoever afflicted either in ſoule or body, either with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or poverty, or any other calamitie whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156762:6"/>if thou poureſt out thy Prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations unto God, it is his owne promiſe that hee will heare thee; for as the <hi>oile did not ceaſe untill they wanted veſsels to receive it,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. ſo there is no end of Gods mercies towards us till we want faith to apprehend it. Say not then deſperately with <hi>Cain,</hi> that <hi>thy ſin is greater then can be forgiven,</hi> for no ſinne is ſo great but God can, ſuch is his power, and God will, ſuch is his goodneſſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the ſame. It is not ſimply thy ſin committed, but thy impenitencie added unto thy ſinne, that makes it irremiſſible in event. Haſt thou beene an Idolater? ſo was <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> haſt thou beene lewde of thy body? ſo was <hi>David;</hi> haſt thou been overtaken with wine? ſo was <hi>Noah;</hi> haſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed thy Lord and Maſter? ſodid <hi>Peter;</hi> haſt thou perſecuted him in his members? ſo did <hi>Paul:</hi> All theſe obtained pardon by prayer and humiliation; they could pleade nothing elſe but mercie, and this mayſt thou plead as well as they. Let us then poſſeſſe our ſouls not in patience only, but in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and ſo oft as we are afflicted let us pray.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſo ſoone as we are afflicted we muſt pray. Thou muſt not put off thy prayers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions unto Almighty God, upon the accompt of many dayes, leſt with that fooliſh rich man thy ſoule be fetcht away this night. Thy body is now ſtrong and lively, truſt it not too far. <hi>Memento, mare vertitur;</hi> the tide may ſoone turn a ſhip, (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) may play upon the Sea with a faire gale, and yet be drownd the ſame day, for a day, an hower, a moneth is enough to overcome thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156762:7"/>things that ſeeme to have beene founded and rooted in Adamant. Let our ſoules bee dreſſed then, like the Lampe of the Tabernacle, at leaſt twice a day, that is, every morning and every eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with prayer and humiliation, and let us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that day wherein we have neglected either Gods Word or Prayer, to be unhappy; for how can I anſwer ſuch ſtrange neglect, when God ſhall be ſo neere me as within me, <hi>about my paths,</hi> and <hi>about my bed,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) if in a whole day I doe not ſo much as once ſpeak to him, or he to me? But the reaſon why oftentimes we defer our prayers, is, becauſe we are afraid leſt God ſhould heare our prayers too ſoone; for there are none of us but are wedded to ſome one beloved ſin or other we are loth to part with; we keep it cloſe within us, as a child doth ſugar (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his tongue, and ſwallow it down by little and little. Thus Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (before his converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) prayed to God for chaſtitie; but yet as he writes of himſelf in his Confeſſions, he was afraid leſt God ſhould heare his prayer too ſoone, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to have his luſt yet a little better ſatisfied before it was quite extinguiſhed. And this is the condition of us all; With the Samaritans we could be content to ſerve God, ſo as we might our Images too: We are loth to make an integrall ſeparation of our ſelves from our ſins, ſaying with <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian, <hi>God be mercifull unto me when I goe into the houſe of Rimmon.</hi> Thus <hi>Lot,</hi> though ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the ſin of Sodome, yet unarmed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another ſin. Thus <hi>Herod,</hi> though in other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156762:7"/>matters he could heare <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> willingly; yet <hi>look thou ſpeak not of Herodias:</hi> But thus to give cloſe and ſecret entertainment to theſe forbidden gueſts, is a matter of dangerous conſequence; for it is in ſin, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> tels it is in Treaſon, <hi>Qui deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berant, deſciverunt,</hi> To admit any the modeſteſt termes of parley with Gods enemies, is utterly to forſake him. Whilſt it is called <hi>to day,</hi> then let us embrace ſalvation; for there is nothing more dangerous then delay: Nay cuſtome of ſinning will ſo endeare thee unto ſin, that it will be death to part with it; like a ſoft and gentle poiſon, the venome whereof being inſenſibly pernitious, worketh death, and yet is never felt working. Put not off thy devotions then as <hi>Foelix</hi> did <hi>Paul, Goe thy wayes for this time, at a more convenient time I will ſend for thee;</hi> or as <hi>Cato</hi> did the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Greeke tongue, till ſeventy yeers old, but as in the corporall, ſo in the ſpirituall diſeaſe of our ſoules, let us uſe prevention, and ſo ſoone as we are afflicted let us pray.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſo long as we are afflicted we muſt pray. We muſt reſolve with holy <hi>Job,</hi> though the Lord ſhould kill me, yet would I wait on his leiſure. Admit thou finde not preſently helpe, in thy firſt or ſecond vexation or trouble, yet we muſt learne to ſtrengthen our faith by that expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience we have had heretofore of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards us, by thoſe things wee have knowne performed: let us learne to hope for thoſe things that are promiſed. Doe I for my owne particular acknowledge to have received much,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156762:8"/>why, let that make me certaine to receive more. <hi>Habenti dabitur,</hi> to him that hath, more ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. When I doubt what I ſhall have, let mee ſearch what I have had at the hands of God; Let me make this reckoning, that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits he hath beſtowed, are bills obligatory, and ſufficient ſureties, that he will further his preſent mercie, and it is ſtill a warrant of his future love, becauſe <hi>Whom he loveth, he loveth unto the end. Abraham,</hi> we know, as he did multiply petition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on petition, ſo ſtill he got more advantage at the hands of God. At firſt Gods promiſe was to <hi>ſpare Sodome for fifty righteous mens ſake,</hi> at laſt hee brought him from fifty unto ten: <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt not be wearie in lifting up his hands, nor we in making our Prayers and ſupplications unto God. <hi>Naaman,</hi> we know, did <hi>waſh ſeven times in Jordan before he was cleanſed;</hi> and ſhall we think then with the men of <hi>Bethulia</hi> to wait but five dayes onely, and then give over? No, but as we muſt pray ſo ſoone as we can, ſo we muſt pray as long as we can; The firſt will croſſe the devils <hi>nimis cito,</hi> and the other his <hi>nimis ſero;</hi> We muſt not then give over at the firſt encounter, but we muſt ſolicite God againe and again, and the ſixt time. And ſo ſo long as we are afflicted we muſt pray.</p>
            <p>Now followes the laſt circumſtance, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever afflicted we muſt pray. <hi>Peter</hi> muſt not deny his Maſter in the High Prieſts hall, nor the Eunuch forget him in the Chariot, nor <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> though in place of deſpaire, nor <hi>Jonas</hi> in the Whales belly, nor <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions den, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156762:8"/>every where we muſt pray. The places Chriſt moſt frequented for Prayer, we reade they were theſe foure: <hi>In Templo, in Deſerto, in Horto, in Crucem.</hi> From whence I will gather theſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Concluſions how to pray: Firſt, <hi>in Templo,</hi> publiquely in the Church, in the midſt of the congregation: For albeit the true worſhip of God be to God in it ſelfe acceptable, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it be, who regardeth not ſo much in what place, as with what affection he is ſerved; yet notwithſtanding the majeſty and holineſſe of the place where God is worſhipped, hath (in regard of us) great vertue, force and efficacie, in that it ſerveth as a ſenſible help to ſtir up devotion, and in this regard, no doubt, bettereth our beſt and holyeſt actions thereby. And therefore although I exhort every where to worſhip God, yet me thinks there is no exhortation ſo fit as that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, O worſhip the Lord in the beauty of holineſſe, Pſ.</hi> 39. for every place is not ſo fit for Divine Service: <hi>Ye ſhall ſeek the place that the Lord ſhall chooſe, and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ye bring your burnt offerings and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and eate before the Lord, Deut.</hi> 12.5, 6. <hi>Moſes</hi> built a Tabernacle for God, and <hi>Solomon</hi> built a Temple; God muſt have his Synagogue, his Temple, where he may be called on; and of that place it may be ſaid, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſpake of the place where he ſlept, <hi>God is in this place.</hi> And yet I would not have you think, that I doe confine God in a circle; <hi>God dwels not in Temples made with hands; Templum Domini</hi> will not ſerve the turne, unleſſe <hi>Dominus Templi</hi> be there: For God as hee is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156762:9"/>not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a reſpecter of perſons; no more he is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a reſpecter of places; but as it was ſaid, where <hi>Helen</hi> is, there is <hi>Troy,</hi> and where the Emperour, there Rome; ſo where but two are gathered together in his name, there he will make the third; for Gods eares are open in all places; <hi>Moſes</hi> in the midſt of the ſea, <hi>Job</hi> on the dunghill, <hi>Jeremy</hi> in the mire, the three children in the fiery furnace calling to God, were heard, as Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> noteth; And yet notwithſtanding we muſt account his houſe of Prayer his eſpeciall place of ſervice; and therefore <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and ſome other of the graveſt Fathers did plainly teach, that the houſe of Prayer it was a Court beautified with the preſence of celeſtiall powers: there we pray, we ſound forth hymnes unto God, having the Angels themſelves intermingled as our aſſociates; and that with reference thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it is that the Apoſtle doth require ſo much decencie to be had in the Church of God, for the <hi>Angels</hi> ſake, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. And therefore they which forſake the Temple of God, and betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to private conventicles and meetings, truly they may have zeale, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whoſe experience hath not found what confuſion of Order, and breach of that ſacred bond of Peace, is cauſed by theſe private mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; how they have rent the body of the Church into divers parts, and divided the people into divers ſects; how they have taught the Sheep to deſpiſe their Paſtors, and alienated the Paſtors from the love of their flocks. To declaim againſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156762:9"/>the ſwarme of evils iſſuing of private Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, is an eaſie labour. I wiſh rather I could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe effectually a remedy, whereby a ſore ſo dangerous might be cured: For certainly, if ſome ſpeedie courſe bee not taken to ſuppreſſe this growing miſchiefe, it may be feared, that in ſome ſhort time, God will be turned out of Churches into barnes, and private houſes, and from thence again, into the fields and Mountains, and under the hedges. This I am ſure, that theſe unlawfull meetings, have occaſioned ſuch altercations, and diſputings in points of Doctrine and Government, that I thinke there is not greater varietie of faces, then there is of fancies and opinions in points of Religion now amongſt us; nay, I thinke there were never ſo many Sects and Schiſmes amongſt the ancient Philoſophhrs, as is to be found in this little Iſland of ours, amongſt us Chriſtians, every contentious and ignorant perſon, cloathing his fancie with the Spirit of God, and his imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the gift of Revelation; ſo as when the truth which is but one, ſhall by this meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unto the ſimple multitude no leſſe variable, then contrary to it ſelfe, the faith of men will ſoone die by degrees, and all Religion held but in ſcorne and contempt. But there are another ſort of men, which refuſe to communicate with us, and thoſe are ſeduced Recuſants; it is their idle boaſt, that their Religion hath built all our Churches: If it be ſo, the more is our griefe, that our Founders ſhould be like the carpenters of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, who building and preparing for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156762:10"/>refuſe to ſave themſelves in it when they have done. But let them urge their claime, and make a religious, conſcionable, and peaceable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; For what is wanting in our Churches, that Chriſtians would deſire to have? Here have wee Chriſt and him crucified; would they feede on on Chriſt? Behold, here in his Supper, his very body and blood, as he ordained it. If they can be <hi>aquilae</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>) not <hi>graculi,</hi> Eagels to fly aloft, and not Jayes to ſeeke their foode on the ground. Here have we Baptiſme by water, and the Word, the Scriptures moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptly publiſhed, the Law, the Goſpel, the ſame <hi>Pater noſter</hi> they brag off. What ſhould aile them then, but that they ſhould joyne with us in one accord, and ſing chearfully that heavenly <hi>Hallelujah, Glory to God on high, peace on earth, good will towards men?</hi> And thus you ſee how we muſt pray, <hi>in Templo,</hi> publiquely in the midſt of the congregation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt pray likewiſe <hi>in Deſerto,</hi> privately. <hi>When thou prayeſt,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>enter into thy chamber, and when thou haſt ſhut the doore, pray unto thy Father which is in ſecret.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I remember, expounds theſe words Allegorically: Enter into thy chamber, (ſaith hee) that is, into thine heart, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit there, and become a fearfull witneſſe to thy ſelfe, of thine owne ſecret evills, and ſhut the doore, that is, cleanſe thine heart from all wicked and wandering cogitations, that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract thy ſoule in her moſt retired meditations.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156762:10"/>But theſe words may be taken as well literally; for this holy and religious duty and ſervice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, concerneth us one way in that we are men, and another way as we are joyned as members of that viſible myſticall body which is the Church. As private men, then it is at our own choice, both for time, place, and forme, as the exigencie of our occaſions require in private; and he that doth not ſet apart ſome ſelect time of the day for the performance of this duty, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely wanting to himſelfe, and careleſſe of his owne ſalvation. But as we doe performe this duty as members of a publique body, it muſt be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and this is thought by ſome ſo much wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier then the other, as a whole ſociety exceeds the worth of any one perſon. For every Prayer, (as conſidered ſingly and ſolely by it ſelfe,) it is like a little ſtick of juniper, that ſends forth a ſmall perfume, but many of theſe together like a fagot, that ſends forth whole pillars of ſmoake, and therefore muſt needes make a farre ſweeter ſmell in the noſtrils of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou muſt pray <hi>in Horto,</hi> in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; that is, in the midſt of all thy pleaſures and delights; and not to be like the wild Aſſe, that never brayeth but when it wanteth fodder; or like the ungratefull Iſraelites, to forget God, whilſt thou ſitteſt by the fleſh-pots of Egypt; or like <hi>Jobs</hi> yong Hindes, that growing up, and wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fat, goe forth, and never returne unto their dammes. For many there are, who never think on God, but when they finde themſelves in great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156762:11"/>extremity and feare; like little children, (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) who when they perceive any immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger, run preſently under the wing of the mother: But thus never to ſeeke after God, but when the crib or the whip ſhall conſtraine, is a bruitiſh ſervility. And certainly, it is greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatorie from that which is moſt predominant in man, if we have not ſometimes a voluntary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe unto God, all other inferiour conſiderations whatſoever laid aſide; and therefore as in our greateſt neceſſity we muſt beg for ſupply of thoſe things we want, ſo in our greateſt abundance and plenty we muſt pray for a continuance of thoſe wee have received, and never entertain a benefit at the hands of God without a thankfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his liberality and goodneſſe, by whoſe providence it is enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt pray <hi>in Cruce,</hi> that is, in the time of affliction and perſecution: Many there are who can be content to pray, and are mindfull of God too, ſo long as they may ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon beds of Ivorie, and have all their hearts can wiſh; but if they be conſtrained to lie downe in the waves of ſorrow, if affliction doe aſſault, why then they are readie preſently to turne their backs, ſtarting aſide like a broken bow; but a true Chriſtian (ſaith Saint <hi>Anguſtine</hi>) he muſt be like a ſtone that is ſquare, that ſtands howſoever you turne it: he muſt not be like <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiahs</hi> ſunne to goe backward, nor like <hi>Joſuahs</hi> ſun to ſtand ſtill, but like <hi>Davids</hi> ſunne, who like a Bridegroome comes out of his chamber, and like a Gyant rejoyceth to runne his courſe; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156762:11"/>though he walke through the valley of teares, yet no other reſolution muſt poſſeſſe his minde then this, <hi>O my God thou art juſt, O my ſoule thou art hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</hi> The heathen man could tell us, that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they are <hi>tributa vivendi,</hi> the tributes of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and therefore we ought to beare them man-like and reſolvedly, and not as thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſouldiers doe, <hi>qui gementes ſequuntur Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem,</hi> but rather imbrace them as thoſe Virgins in <hi>Euſebius</hi> did their martyrdomes, running there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>tanquam ad nuptias,</hi> as if they were to meet their Bridegroome: For the godly are purged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but it is to be made the better: Is gold the worſe becauſe it is refined? or wheat becauſe it is fanned? the light would not be ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, were it not for that uſuall intercourſe of darkneſſe. Too much honey doth turne to gall, and too much joy, even ſpirituall, may make us wantons: Thou mayeſt a while be toſſed up and down in this troubleſome world, like <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, amongſt the waters, but yet the Lord will at length remember <hi>Noah,</hi> and then all theſe waters ſhall be abated. The <hi>Romans</hi> we know did never fight and triumph both in one place, their bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tails were commonly fought in <hi>Africk</hi> or in <hi>Aſia,</hi> but their place of triumph it was in <hi>Rome:</hi> ſo we muſt not looke to contend and receive a Crowne of victory both at once; our time of ſuffering is here in this world, our crowne of reward that comes hereafter: for when our ſoules immortall ſhall be once ſeparated from our mortall bodies, and diſpoſed of God, then comes beauty for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156762:12"/>aſhes, oile of joy for mourning, garments of gladneſſe for this ſpirit of heavineſſe; ſo that the contemplation of this future happineſſe, muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe it ſelfe betwixt us and our afflictions: and certainly the troubles and afflictions of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, are evermore mingled and allayed with many delights and comforts. Here we are <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, but <hi>yet alwayes rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. For there is a Spirit of comfort within us, alwayes <hi>helping our infirmities:</hi> If we be buffeted or beaten for the Goſpel of Chriſt, then this Spirit tells us that it is <hi>an honour to ſuffer for the name of Jeſus:</hi> If poverty oppreſſe us, then the Spirit teacheth us to <hi>be content with what we have.</hi> What if <hi>Benjamin</hi> have a double portion? ſome others, worldly riches more then I? per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it is all the portion theſe men can hope for to inherit. What if I be made here on earth one of the leſſe honourable members of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the foot, and not the hand or the eye? it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for me that I am a fellow heire with the nobleſt members of the body, and perhaps God will recompence this preſent want of mine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after with more abundant honour. If the death of ſome deare friend, the loſſe of thine office or eſtate, or any ſuch thing be thine affliction, why the Spirit is able to teach and inſtruct thee, that all things wee enjoy in this preſent life, they are but lent us, and therefore we muſt account of them all but as things borrowed from ſome friend or neighbour, who may call for them back againe at their pleaſure. Neither muſt it trouble
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156762:12"/>us what inſtruments are uſed for the fetching home of theſe earthly commodities, whether fire or water, theeves or ſickneſſe, no more then if thy neighbour who hath lent thee a ſaw or a hatchet, or any other houſhold thing, ſhould appoint ſome fooliſh or diſhoneſt ſervant to bring it home again, and to re-mand it.</p>
            <p>Let us learne then in all dutifull obedience to ſubmit our ſelves to Gods good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; For though our troubles be great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet I have an aſſured confidence, that God will never ſuffer his ſtrength and ſpirit utterly to forſake us, or give us altogether over to the rage and madneſſe of thoſe that hate us. For this is Gods conſtant method of proceeding, he doth either protect and keep the righteous out of all calamities, or elſe if they fall upon him, he condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth him ſafe through them, and permitteth them not to be miſeries; He either gives him honours, and promotions, and wealth, or elſe more benefit by wanting of them, then if he had them all at his owne will and pleaſure; he either filleth his houſe with plenty of all good things, or elſe makes him a ſallet of greene herbs, more ſweet then all the ſacrifices of the ungodly. Let us not then with the ungratefull Iſraelites, murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God for any affliction ſent unto us, for God knows whereof thou art made, he ſees how thy nature ſtands inclined. If thou ſhouldſt alwayes heare the ſweet tune of pleaſure and delight, as it were the melodie of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> inſtruments, perhaps thou wouldſt preſently fall downe and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156762:13"/>worſhip this Babyloniſh Idol. The Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was even at the point of cleane forgetting himſelfe, and ſo ſtraying from his right minde, but that <hi>thy rod</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath been my ſupporter.</hi> And the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> if he had not had the corraſive of ſharp and bitter ſtrokes, his heart would have gone neer to have ſwolne with that great abundance of heavenly revelations; for we are prone by nature to forget our ſelves, and therefore we had need of ſome buffetings of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to make us reflect upon our owne weakneſſe. The children of Iſrael whilſt they lived in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity at home, would neither hearken nor obey; but being in baniſhment, and under captivity, then whilſt they ſate by the waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they could weep to <hi>remember thee, O Sion.</hi> For there is not any affliction, how ſhort ſoever, but doth more truly informe a mans underſtanding in a day, then all the grave ſpeeches, and ſubtileſt diſputations of the Philoſophers in a yeare; Then we begin to remember that there is a God, and that we our ſelves are but men; Then we admire no man, and deſpiſe no man, ſeeing by the condition of our owne frailty, that no man is ſo ſecured of his riches, his honours, his life, or his poſſeſſions, but that he may be deprived of theſe, or any of theſe, the very next day, or houre to come: for it is not the heighth or eminencie of place or meanes that can exempt us from caſualties or inconveniences. Tall men (we know) are as ſubject unto fevers, as men of lower ſtature; and great Empires and Kingdomes we ſee by wofull experience are as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156762:13"/>eaſily diſturbed, as the State of pety Princes. For thoſe who are advanced to the higheſt pitch of honour, I cannot better compare then to the firſt letter of a Patent, or limb'd booke, which we know hath great and large flouriſhes, yet ſtill it is but a letter: So thoſe kind of men, they may have large flouriſhes, high and ſwelling Titles, great Honours and preferments, yet ſtill they are but men, mortall men, incident to every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, griefe and infirmity as well as others; and thus we ſee afflictions are the onely ſoveraign meanes to bring us to a right ſenſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelves; and therefore whatſoever our condition or eſtate be, let us learne therewith to be content; for this world is a kind of ſtage-play, where there muſt be Actors of all ſorts; one man acts a King, another a Lord, a third a cripple, a fourth a beggar: Now one of theſe Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours am I, and therefore whatſoever part it ſhall pleaſe the great God of heaven and earth to aſſign me to repreſent, I muſt perform it with cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and alacrity; If my lot be to act a beggar, or a cripple, whilſt another man acts a Prince or a Lord, why, the will of God be done, all my care ſhall be, to act my beggars or my cripples part, with the beſt grace and comlineſſe that I can; knowing that the change of fortune here on this great Theatre, is but like the change of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the leſſe; for when upon the one and upon the other every one weares but his owne skinne, the Players are all alike. And thus we ſee how we muſt pray, <hi>in Cruce,</hi> in the time of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156762:14"/>and perſecution. And thus we finde this laſt circumſtance to be verified, that is, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever afflicted we muſt pray.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we may offend in doing thoſe things which we ought to doe, as the Scribes and Phariſees we know did offend in their Faſtings and Prayers, it will not be amiſſe, I think, to ſhew what Prayers muſt be avoided. They muſt be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>temerariae, timidae,</hi> nor <hi>frigidae.</hi> Firſt, <hi>temerariae,</hi> raſh or unadviſed prayers, either for matter or for manner. Firſt, for matter; we muſt not pray for thoſe things that are unlawfull; nay in thoſe things which are good and lawfull in themſelves, we muſt put a difference; for all Gods gifts I may not unfitly reduce to theſe two heads, either ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, which God propoſeth to us as the laſt end of our endeavours, or elſe temporall, which hee ſends unto us as means and helps, the better to ſtrengthen us in our weak endeavours. Now then in ſuing for theſe, we muſt pray diverſly; for in praying for temporall things, we muſt ask upon condition; but in praying for ſpirituall things, we muſt aske without exception. <hi>Jacob</hi> may pray for food and rayment, <hi>Solomon</hi> for wiſdome, <hi>Job</hi> for his children; but yet as it is <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. <hi>If God will:</hi> So that the clauſe which our Saviour in the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his Agonie did expreſſe, we in Petitions of like nature muſt ever imply, <hi>Pater, ſi poſsibile eſt,</hi> If it ſtand with thy good will and pleaſure: For oftentimes when we reflect only upon our ſelves, and our own inordinate appetites and deſires, we faſten upon God thoſe unſeaſonable offices which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156762:14"/>pleaſe him not, and think oft times we crave fiſh, when indeed it proves a ſerpent. And therefore as it comes to paſſe in weighty and maſſie bodies, that they have certaine trepidations and wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings before they fixe and ſettle; ſo in all our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions and deſires for theſe temporall things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we may ſo eaſily erre, and be deceived, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we fixe and ſettle our reſolutions to beg this or that at the hands of God, we ſhould have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine trepidations and waverings, and revolve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe within our ſelves, whether the things we ask for may be allowable in the ſight of God. And thus we ſee for the matter of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, it muſt not be raſh or unadviſed; we muſt not pray for thoſe things that are unlavvfull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the manner of our Prayers, they muſt not be raſh neither, but upon due and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation; it being a thing monſtrous even in the courſe of nature, to have any thing concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and borne both in one inſtant. Conſider but the irkeſome deformities and manifold confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are occaſioned by theſe endleſſe and ſenſeleſſe effuſions of indigeſted Prayers, ſo that the worthieſt part of our Chriſtian dutie towards God, is by this meanes oftentimes in moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner, both diſgraced and abuſed; for if ſpeaking to an earthly Prince, we utter nothing raſhly, but upon deliberate counſell and advice; how much more ought we to be careful, ſtanding in Gods preſence, in his Temple, the place where his honour dwelleth, and ſpeaking in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God, men, and Angels? and therefore they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156762:15"/>cannot be excuſed, that ſo far abuſe the valuation of prayer, as if there were no difference betwixt praying and ſelling of Doves in the Temple, and inſtead of poliſhing the chiefe corner ſtone, dawbe it up with nothing elſe but filthy untempered morter; never framing their Prayers by medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beforehand, but contriving them all on the ſuddain, expecting in the very inſtant that God ſhould miraculouſly (as to that widow of <hi>Sarepta</hi>) multiply their little oile for the diſcharge of ſo great a dutie. Hence it is that all ſet forme of Prayer, is almoſt brought cleane out of taſte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we make God like unto our ſelves, and judge him by our owne bellies, imagining that God doth loathe to have the ſame ſupplications often reiterated, even as we doe loathe to be every day fed without alteration or change of dyet; but if it be ſo, why then did God himſelfe leave unto his Prieſts the very ſpeech wherewith they were to bleſſe the people? <hi>Num.</hi> 9. Or why did our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt leave unto us a Prayer of his owne, whereby to frame all other Prayers with efficacie, yet without ſuperfluity of words? For in very deede, if our beſt and moſt conſiderate deſires, have ſome things in them to be pardoned, it muſt needes be held a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable preſumption to thinke that raſh and unadviſed Prayers, can be meritorious or worthy to be rewarded. And therefore to except againſt ſet order and forme of Prayer, doth ſavour of much pride, and but little charity; for how many poore ſouls are there in the world, who not being
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156762:15"/>able upon every occaſion to frame Prayers anew for themſelves, by this meanes ſhould be abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all helps and comforts they might receive from others?</p>
            <p>Secondly, our prayers they muſt not be <hi>timidae,</hi> we muſt deſpaire nothing at all of Gods bounty, knowing his ability ſtill the ſame to perfect his power in weakneſſe: For ſhall the hand of little <hi>David,</hi> (O thou moſt mighty) if a ravenous beare break into his fold, and ſteale away a ſheep; or if a roaring Lion ſallie out of his den, and rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a lamb from him, be able to deliver them both from the mouth of the beare, and pawe of the Lyon, and ſhalt not thou be much more able to reſcue the ſheepe of thy fold, and the lambs of thy flock? ſurely yes, if <hi>David</hi> delivered his lambs from the pawe of the beare, thou delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt <hi>David</hi> from the mouth of the lion; if he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his flock by which he lived, why then thou muſt needes love thine for whom thou dyedſt; <hi>ſunt ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quater<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beati,</hi> they are thrice and foure times happie, who make God their ſhield with <hi>David,</hi> and the Lord their ſure defence with <hi>Moſes,</hi> for he is able to defend them from the ſtrongeſt enemy, and to give them victory in the day of battail.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, our prayers they muſt not be <hi>frigidae,</hi> we muſt not pray coldly, but earneſtly. If with <hi>Hezekiah</hi> we poure out our prayers unto God in the bitterneſſe of our hearts, then we ſhall be heard: but if we doe nothing but chatter like a ſwallow, and thinke to be heard through our vain
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156762:16"/>babling we much deceive our ſelves: For God regards not ſo much <hi>verba dicentis,</hi> as <hi>corda oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> and therefore there were two faults which our Lord and Saviour himſelfe eſpecially reproved in prayer; the firſt when oſtentation cauſed it to be open; and the other when ſuperſtition made it to be long: The things which God regards is, how vertuous their minds are, and not how copious their tongues in prayer; how well they thinke, and not how long they ſpeake; for the words, be they never ſo few, may beget too many, when they benefit neither the ſpeaker nor the hearer: but he that ſpeaketh no more then edifieth, is undeſervedly reprehended; it is not <hi>oratio</hi> that prevaileth with God; but <hi>oratio ſancti:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Pliny</hi> makes mention of a certain precious ſtone, that hath many vertues in it, yet being put into a dead mans skull, loſeth all: So Prayer, though of it ſelfe very effectuall, yet comming from a dead heart, it helpes as little as the gate, the cripple, that was called beautifull. Be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull unto me O God, ſaith devout <hi>Bernard,</hi> for there I commit moſt ſinne, where I ſhould leaſt offend, in thy Temple, at thine Altar, even in thine owne preſence. When we poure out our Prayers and Supplications unto thee, we make it onely a matter of forme and cuſtome, we ſpeake with our lips, but our hearts are farre from thee; and thus we make a mockery of God, deſiring him to attend that which we our ſelves are not willing to attend; we turne that to poiſon, which might be our foode; we lay fooliſhly thoſe eggs,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156762:16"/>out of which our wofull overthrow is afterwards hatcht. And thus we ſee what prayers muſt be avoided; they muſt be neither <hi>temerariae, timidae,</hi> nor <hi>frigidae.</hi> And thus have I gone through the particulars of this Text; there remaineth nothing beſides, but that we put this duty of prayer into practice and execution, to deſire of God a bleſſing upon theſe weake endeavours, that they may be to his glory and your own comfort, which God of his infinite mercie and goodneſſe grant unto us, and that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with the Father and bleſſed Spirit, be all honour and glory now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
